<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Discourse of the necessity of encouraging mechanick industry wherein is plainly proved that luxury and the want of artisans labour became the ruin of the four grand monarchies of the world in the former age, and of Spain and other countries in this : and the promoting of manual trades the rise of the Dutch, Germans, &amp;c. : parallel'd and compared with, and shewn to be practicable under the present constitution of England.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 78 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A36104</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1606</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12440</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12277731</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12277731</idno>
            <idno type="VID">58535</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A36104)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 58535)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 140:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Discourse of the necessity of encouraging mechanick industry wherein is plainly proved that luxury and the want of artisans labour became the ruin of the four grand monarchies of the world in the former age, and of Spain and other countries in this : and the promoting of manual trades the rise of the Dutch, Germans, &amp;c. : parallel'd and compared with, and shewn to be practicable under the present constitution of England.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[5], 36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Chiswell ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. 36.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Industrial arts --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Industrial arts --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:58535:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58535:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DISCOURSE OF THE NECESSITY of ENCOURAGING <hi>Mechanick Induſtry:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein is plainly proved, That Luxury and the want of Artiſans Labour, became the Ruin of the four Grand Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chies of the World, in the Former Age, and of <hi>Spain</hi> and other Countries, in This: and the Promoting of manual Trades the riſe of the <hi>Dutch, Germans,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Parallel'd and compared with, and ſhewn to be pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticable under the preſent Conſtitution of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LICENS'D, <hi>Aug.</hi> 23d. 1689.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Chiſwell,</hi> at the <hi>Roſe</hi> and <hi>Crown</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard. MDCXC.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:58535:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58535:2"/>
            <head>The PREFACE to the READER.</head>
            <p>SO viſibly is this Kingdom degenerated from the great Atchievements of <hi>Vertue</hi> and <hi>Induſtry,</hi> into all the ſoft Indulgences of <hi>Sloth,</hi> and of an effeminate and luxurious courſe of Life (the former the Dignity, and Preſervation, the latter the Reproach and Ruine of a State) as makes it a Work of as great Seaſonableneſs as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, to endeavour a Recommendation of ſuch laborious Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provements, as may, in ſome meaſure, regain to us that high Reputation and Eſteem in the World, which was juſtly due to the induſtrious management of our careful and active Predeceſſors, and which our preſent <hi>Idleneſs</hi> and too appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent a neglect of <hi>Mechanical,</hi> and other, Employments, has either incurred a <hi>Forfeiture</hi> of, or at leaſt can pretend no good <hi>Title</hi> unto. The nature of this Subject, chiefly rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to matters of <hi>Trade</hi> and <hi>Buſineſs,</hi> ſeems not to require any great Art of <hi>Rhetorick,</hi> or accuracy of Expreſſion in the Compoſure; and ſo comes not with thoſe Ornaments and Embelliſhments of Oratory, and of a correct and eloquent Style, which are due to more learned and refined Diſcourſes. 'Twill (I preſume) be ſatisfactory to the judicious Reader, and to Men of <hi>Action,</hi> if they find any thing of Weight, and ſubſtance in it, that may be of Force to evince; and perſwade them, of the reaſonableneſs of what it propoſes, and that what is here offered for the promoting of <hi>Mecha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical</hi> and other Arts, is neither <hi>impracticable, unneceſſary,</hi> nor yet <hi>unſeaſonable</hi> in the preſent Juncture of Affairs, and this Age of declenſion from <hi>Labour</hi> and <hi>Induſtry:</hi> But on the contrary, will (if purſu'd) derive publick Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages upon the <hi>State,</hi> as well as tend to the Preſervation and Advancement of private and individual intereſts, which from
<pb facs="tcp:58535:3"/>the Methods laid down in this ſmall Tract, we find to have already accrued to other well-governed Commonwealths, in a due and regular Exerciſe and Incouragement of Arts and Occupations of all ſorts. This being the principal Aim and Scope of the following Diſcourſe, will not (I hope) upon its peruſal appear altogether void of, or defective in its Deſign; which to enforce by prevalent, if not, cogent Inſtances and Inducements; I have attempted to give the Reader a ſuccinct View, or an Abridgment of thoſe National Miſchiefs and Calamities; and theſe the moſt remarkable, both in Antient and Modern Governments, which have been entailed upon <hi>Luxury</hi> and <hi>Idleneſs,</hi> how they conſumed the very Vitals, and became deſtructive of the four great <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchies</hi> of the World, the <hi>Aſſyrian, Perſian, Graecian</hi> and <hi>Roman:</hi> How ſeveral Countries in this Age <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> waſted and depopulated; ſome from an high and flouriſhing, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending to a moſt indigent and contemptible Eſtate; others remaining a ſterile and uncultivated Chaos, ſtocked with a ſort of <hi>rational Brutes</hi> (pardon the <hi>illogical</hi> Expreſſion) which have nothing but human Shape to denominate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Men; and the ſource of all this beſtial Inhumanity or barbarous Rudeneſs, is the want of <hi>Arts</hi> and <hi>Labour</hi> among them. On the other Hand, I have ſhewn you the prodigious Riſe of other places, from an abject to a very wealthy and honourable Condition, effected by means of their great Induſtry; and in fine, have parallel'd both, in an applicatory Relation to our preſent Conſtitution and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as well demonſtrating how our luxurious Eaſe and Plenty, and the diſcountenancing of Labour among us, threaten an Introduction of that Ruin, which has attended other Nations, that ſunk into Voluptuouſneſs and Sloth; as preſcribing of other Kingdoms as <hi>Patterns</hi> of our imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, who are famed for their Induſtry, will in Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, confer upon us proportionable Emoluments and Advantages.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:58535:3"/>
            <head>A DISCOURSE Of the NECESSITY of Mechanick Induſtry, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THat which the Great <hi>Jehovah</hi> juſtly inflicted upon <hi>Adam,</hi> as a Puniſhment due to his violation of, and apoſtaſie from his origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal and priſtine eſtate of Innocency, <hi>In the Sweat of thy Face ſhalt thou eat Bread</hi>] was in the days of <hi>Solomon</hi> turn'd from a Curſe into a Bleſſing: For, this being pronounc'd by God to <hi>Adam,</hi> as well in the nature of a Command (obliging him and his Poſterity, then in his Loins, to a laborious courſe of life for the future) as by way of a juſt Judgment upon him for his voluntary defection; did conſequently derive many ſecular felicities and enjoyments upon ſuch as lived in obedience and conformity thereunto. The <hi>Golden Age,</hi> or rather that momentany ſtate of Integrity, (not ſo in its own nature, but of Man's continuance in it) was indeed exempt from all painful Anxiety or laborious Toil. <hi>Nature,</hi> as a plentiful Store-houſe, furniſh'd eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:58535:4"/>living Creature with proper and diſtinct Proviſions, without any Cultivation or Improvement, Art or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry; the whole Univerſe abounded with plenty of its own production, and ſeem'd, like a <hi>Tree</hi> overcharg'd with <hi>Fruit,</hi> to bow down to <hi>Adam,</hi> that ſo he might eaſily, and without any trouble, pluck of all ſorts, except that of the <hi>forbidden,</hi> which tho' but one, muſt needs be taſted by his extravagantly-delicate Palate, which ſowred and imbit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd all the pleaſing ſweetneſs of the reſt; and thoſe things which he had ſo freely fed upon before, muſt now be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with ſorrow all the days of his Life.</p>
            <p>Man thus wilfully deſcending into a laps'd condition, from his free and happy eſtate in <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> the whole World, and all the creatures in it, (as a Curſe appendent to his <hi>Fall</hi>) by the immediate deſignation of Divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, became degenerated from their admirable ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerviency, and uſefulneſs, ſo fitly accommodated to the conveniency of Mankind in their firſt Inſtitution. That which had of it ſelf brought forth <hi>Fruits,</hi> and variety of <hi>Herbs, fit for the uſe of Man,</hi> muſt now be cumber'd with <hi>Thorns</hi> and <hi>Thiſtles:</hi> Nature is now ſo far declin'd from her firſt eſtate, that Art and Induſtry are indiſpenſably requir'd to preſerve her from Ruin; and the <hi>Breach</hi> made by the Fall of <hi>Adam,</hi> muſt either be <hi>repair'd</hi> by humane diligence, or elſe ſhe will ſink under her own weight, and return (at leaſt by gradual approaches) to her pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive <hi>Chaos</hi> and Confuſion. This being then the ſtate of Affairs under the Fall, ſo different from, and inferiour to that of <hi>Original Innocence,</hi> which naturally flow'd with an abundant affluence of all worldly Bleſſings and Enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and which ſeem'd like ſo many <hi>Corrivals</hi> equally contending which ſhould firſt <hi>court</hi> Man's acceptance, and invite him to ſolace himſelf with them, rather than require a laborious ſearch, or indefatigable toil, in their purſuit. It remains then, That whoever would under
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:58535:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>this <hi>laps'd Oeconomy</hi> and degenerated <hi>Government</hi> of the World, arrive to any tolerable degree of felicity in it, or to a participation of the Divine Favours, and ſtill boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful Proviſions of Soveraign Providence; that the way to compaſs theſe naturally deſired Accommodations, is, by <hi>Labour</hi> and <hi>Induſtry;</hi> by a diligent purſuit, and an induſtrious management in the World. For, ſince the <hi>State</hi> of <hi>Original Purity</hi> ſoon expir'd, and that pains and toil is not only the <hi>Curſe,</hi> but <hi>Condition</hi> of the <hi>laps'd,</hi> which God has appointed us to make uſe of, if we would taſte of the Comforts and Emoluments of humane Life: it is plain then, that it is as well a Duty preſcrib'd them from God, as the moſt conducive Expedient for mens Intereſt and Advantage, to apply themſelves with vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance to their reſpective Vocations and Capacities. And this is an undeniable Truth, not only capable of illuſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from ſeveral Inſtances in the infant days of the World, which may be derived from the Patriarchs, whoſe <hi>Labour</hi> and <hi>Induſtry</hi> were the marks of their <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Dignity;</hi> but is alſo evident from the <hi>Gentile</hi> Kings in this Caſe: as for inſtance, The King of <hi>Moab,</hi> who was a Sheepmaſter. And however the <hi>Mechanick</hi> and <hi>Rural</hi> Employments are now (by the vanity of the Age) become contemptible; yet we find, that he that was the moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent Judge of theſe matters, made choice of two of the firſt Kings of his People out of ſuch. And we do not read, That Royalty in them put a period to the Employments of the Fathers, ſo as not to deſcend to their Children. On the contrary, we read, That <hi>Abſolom</hi> had his <hi>Sheep-ſhearers</hi> and his <hi>Corn Fields</hi> in his own management; as appears by remarkable inſtances. But now the prodigious growth of the World, as well in <hi>Impiety</hi> as in <hi>Mankind,</hi> is arriv'd to that height, that <hi>Nimrods</hi> are rather choſe than <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids,</hi> and Government oppreſt with a greater burthen of Labour and Toil, than that which is annex'd to the <hi>Plough.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:58535:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Seeing then that even the Throne is not exempt from Labour, and conſequently he that ſits upon it not diveſted from Care and Anxiety; it ſeems but reaſonable, that there be an exact <hi>Harmony</hi> and <hi>Conſort</hi> betwixt the <hi>Prince</hi> and the <hi>Subject,</hi> and that every <hi>String</hi> in the grand <hi>Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of the World ſhould be wound up to its height, that ſo there might be no <hi>jarrs.</hi> In order whereunto, it ſhall be my work to ſhew, That tho' it is impoſſible to bring men to conformity in all points of Labour and Induſtry, yet that 'tis extream eaſie to effect ſuch a Reformation, as might free this Kingdom from that <hi>load</hi> and <hi>oppreſſion</hi> of uſeleſs men, under which it labours ſo much at preſent; and yet not part with them, but rather take ſuch methods, whereby every individual perſon may become a profitable Member to the whole Community. For, tho' this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom is plentifully ſtock'd with too many Perſons, who are addicted to <hi>Idleneſs</hi> and <hi>Sloth;</hi> yet has it too few mouths in general, and cannot be accounted above one third Peopled, if compared with other parts of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe.</p>
            <p>And therefore, in this Diſcourſe, I ſhall <hi>Firſt</hi> ſhew the <hi>Miſchiefs</hi> that attend thoſe Countries, where Men are ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd to live without honeſt Employments.</p>
            <p>And in the <hi>Second</hi> place, ſhall particularize ſome In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, ſetting forth, how men are oblig'd to Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in ſome Kingdoms, and the good effects which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult from that Engagement.</p>
            <p>And in the <hi>Third</hi> place, ſhall demonſtrate with what good ſucceſs the ſame might be effected in this Nation.</p>
            <p>In reference to the firſt of theſe Particulars; If we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult Hiſtory, whether ancient or modern, we ſhall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly there find, that <hi>Idleneſs</hi> has, in all Ages, been the <hi>Nurſe</hi> and <hi>Parent</hi> of <hi>Voluptuouſneſs</hi> and <hi>Effeminacy,</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:58535:5"/>which gradually encreaſing in proportion to a conſtant diminution of Labour and Induſtry, finally brought in irreverſible deſtruction upon ſuch Countries, where they gain'd the aſcendant, and did predominate.</p>
            <p>Of this, the Monarchy of the <hi>Aſſyrians</hi> is a pregnant and remarkable inſtance, who degenerating from thoſe maſculine and great Atchievements (which firſt gave the riſe to their <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Greatneſs</hi>) into a libidinous and an intemperate courſe of life, became an eaſie Prey to <hi>Cyrus</hi> the Great.</p>
            <p>And thus it hapned to the <hi>Perſian Monarchy,</hi> which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over run with Eaſe, Luxury, and Riot, with ſoft and effeminate Delights, and wanton Pleaſures, withall man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Delicacy and Licentiouſneſs, ſeem'd to the Great <hi>Alexander</hi> rather like Beaſts fitted for the ſlaughter, than for uſe and labour, and gave his Warlike <hi>Macedonians</hi> more trouble to diſrobe them of that Pageantry and ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptuous Apparel which, like ſo many Theatrical Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dees, they came vainly adorn'd with to Battel; than they found in obtaining of an eaſie Conqueſt over thoſe puſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanimous and gaudy <hi>Perſians,</hi> who ſcarce gave any oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition.</p>
            <p>But then, how quickly do we find the <hi>Scene</hi> chang'd in this mighty <hi>Conqueror,</hi> who no ſooner began to conſult his pleaſures, and to foſter up himſelf in <hi>idleneſs</hi> and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate exceſs, but this very man (who had been the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of the Univerſe) becomes a Scorn and Contempt to his own Souldiers. Whilſt he purſu'd the <hi>Macedonian</hi> ſtrictneſs and followed the <hi>genius</hi> of his native Country in a warlike Induſtry, ſo long they adored him as a God: but when he began to wear the <hi>effeminate habit</hi> of the <hi>Perſians,</hi> and to accuſtom himſelf to their <hi>Vices,</hi> even his greateſt <hi>Favourites</hi> hardly accounted him a Man; whoſe Debauchery and Intemperance ſoon put a period to the Life of that illuſtrious Prince, and to the <hi>Macedonian</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:58535:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>which otherwiſe might have been of a laſting dura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and continuance.</p>
            <p>The like ill deſtiny attended the <hi>Roman</hi> Monarchy, when the <hi>Turks</hi> (who had been conſtantly inur'd to hardſhip and perpetual Toil) found the others a People uneaſie with their Plenty, and ſo burthen'd with their time, that 'twas difficult to find waies enough how to ſpend it.</p>
            <p>And, 'twas (doubtleſs) foreſeen by that grand <hi>Impoſtor Mahomet,</hi> that <hi>Idleneſs</hi> and <hi>Luxury</hi> would, if indulg'd, ſo gradually enervate that mighty Empire, as ſoon to bring it to deſtruction; for the prevention whereof, like a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle <hi>Legiſlator,</hi> he enjoin'd it for a <hi>Law,</hi> which even their very Emperors were not to be exempted from; namely, to eat no more than the Labour of his Hands could pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe every day. 'Twould be an infinite undertaking to enumerate the ſeveral Miſeries which at this day attend upon thoſe People, who are denied the benefit of <hi>Arts</hi> and <hi>Labour.</hi> How do the wild <hi>Arabs</hi> live, and aſſociate with their <hi>Herds?</hi> from whom, beſides the erectneſs of their ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, no other mark of diſtinction is ſo viſible upon them, as that they are the more careful Beaſts in providing for their Companions.</p>
            <p>We may ſee in another ſhape the deſolate <hi>Americans;</hi> thoſe of them eſpecially who inhabit the <hi>Northern parts,</hi> where the Men account it a degradation to their Sex, to expoſe themſelves to any Pains for the Food they eat; but believe it to be a Duty incumbent upon the Women, to make proviſion for ſuch as they bring into the World. And this Brutiſh <hi>Sloth</hi> and <hi>Stupidity</hi> is attended with as ſignal and extraordinary a Judgment; for notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that, the Country, as to healthfulneſs and other conveniencies of humane life, is <hi>inferiour</hi> to none in <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope;</hi> and beſides that, <hi>Polygamy</hi> is allowed and practis'd amongſt them; and, that they will no longer retain any
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:58535:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>Woman whom they find to be barren or unfruitful; yet are they ſo few and inconſiderable in number, as by a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable computation, might be thought not to be the Progeny of one Family, in leſs than an Hundred years.</p>
            <p>But to come nearer home, we find the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> by the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count given us in their own <hi>Hiſtories,</hi> written in their <hi>Mother Tongue,</hi> to have been the moſt miſerable People in the Univerſe, when the <hi>Engliſh</hi> firſt arrived amongſt them. And, That then, altho' they lived <hi>promiſcuouſly,</hi> as to the uſe of Women, yet the Souls of that Kingdom were not ſo numerous, upon the <hi>Engliſh</hi> firſt reduction of them, as they afterwards were, in the Reign of K. <hi>James</hi> the Firſt, notwithſtanding that their frequent and reite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated Rebellions had, by a whole <hi>Series</hi> of War &amp; Slaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for ſome Ages, conſum'd a vaſt, or rather incredible, multitude of People amongſt them. The Reaſons which they aſſign for a Solution of this ſeeming <hi>Paradox,</hi> are two: Firſt, they ſay, That before the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Conqueſt they lived in great <hi>Idleneſs</hi> and <hi>Sloth,</hi> having neither <hi>Arts</hi> nor any thing of labour amongſt them; which put them upon a neceſſity of committing of what <hi>Rapin</hi> and <hi>Spoil</hi> they could, and continually to rob and prey upon one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; for, another man's Herds being more numerous than his Neighbours, ſeem'd juſt grounds to him of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king War with him; and ſo mutually cruel and barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous they were upon ſuch occaſions, that 'tis obſerved in all their <hi>Poems</hi> (for ſuch they had amongſt them) that there is not to be found one of <hi>Mirth;</hi> nor to this day have they any Muſical Note or Tune (tho' they afford ſome variety) which is not <hi>melancholy</hi> and <hi>doleful.</hi> The Second Reaſon they give for their being more numerous now than in former Ages, is, That the <hi>Engliſh Laws</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> having introduc'd <hi>Arts</hi> and <hi>Labour</hi> amongſt them, they now, by vertue of their own Induſtry, make proviſion for their Children, and are early in their Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:58535:7"/>that ſo they may be eas'd of their Charge. And, though the maintenance which they now provide for their Children, be ſtill very mean and contemptible, yet however it is ſuch, as to preſerve life, which in former Ages they were not able to compaſs. Nor were they at all ſollicitous what became of the Fruit of their Luſts, which perhaps was ſo intermixt, as 'twas difficult to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh or claim a <hi>Property.</hi> And now, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that they are bounded from theſe Exorbitances by the reſtraint of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Laws and Conſtitutions, which are found to be a ſtricter Curb and Obligation upon them than that of their <hi>Superſtitious</hi> Devotion; which gives a known Latitude and Indulgence in that and other Sins; yet are they not now utterly free from, but, as 'tis ſaid, rather frequently addicted to the ſame Vice.</p>
            <p>Nor has the good Example of the <hi>Engliſh Induſtry</hi> been of that prevalence among ſuch of them, as entitle them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Gentlemen (who are very numerous in that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom) to aſſume the moſt honourable and gentileſt Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments relating to <hi>Trade,</hi> though at the ſame time they are ready to ſtarve for want of ſuſtenance, which they had rather beg or ſteal, than <hi>labour</hi> for.</p>
            <p>This has viſibly, and to a demonſtration, been the ruin of that Kingdom, for that the moſt uſeful and beſt men amongſt them either are forced to <hi>foreign</hi> Service, and ſo neceſſitated to deſert their Country, or are executed for <hi>Robberies, Murthers, &amp;c.</hi> or, which is not the leaſt in ſtrumental to their deſtruction, periſh for want of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency and neceſſary Proviſions; an irregular Life bringing Diſtempers upon them, that ſhortens their daies; for, it is a common obſervation, That among the many Thouſands that live, as they call it, by <hi>coſhering,</hi> there is rarely ſeen an <hi>old man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereas had the <hi>Iriſh</hi> been induſtrious, and had been educated to Arts and Labour, they had kept out thoſe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:58535:7"/>Numbers of <hi>Mechanicks</hi> that went from <hi>England</hi> into that Kingdom; and by that means might have been Maſters of their own Country, notwithſtanding their Subje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to <hi>England;</hi> I mean they might have been Maſters, in this Senſe, ſo as to have had the Command of <hi>Trade</hi> and Buſineſs. But Divine Providence ſaw it not fit to put Opportunity into their Hands, as that would have done, whereby to capacitate them to act greater Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barities by their Numbers: Whereas both now and in the former <hi>Rebellion,</hi> they have, for their own Service, preſerved abundance of Artizans of all ſorts, without whom they could not ſubſiſt, which otherwiſe had felt the unſupportable effects of their bloody and inhuman Cruelties. But having now done with theſe Excreſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of <hi>Spain,</hi> from whence they pretend to have ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginally ſprung; let us ſee how thoſe which they lay claim to for their <hi>Anceſtours,</hi> have throve in their Averſion to <hi>Induſtry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If we deſcend to a particular view of the State of that Kingdom, in all its Reſpects and Circumſtances, it may reaſonably be accounted a Prodigy in Nature: And as by a vulgar Miſtake, ſome term a <hi>Defect</hi> in Nature to be a <hi>monſtrous</hi> Production; we may more rationally af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, That <hi>Spain</hi> hath made it ſelf ſo by <hi>Sloth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Take it in the Conveniency of its Situation, Ferti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of Soil, in the Advantages of its Rich Mines in the <hi>Indies,</hi> (which if rightly mannaged would be ſo) and it might be reaſonably accounted almoſt an abſolute Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibility, to be reduced to that extreme Poverty an Scarcity of Men, wherein it now ſtands.</p>
            <p>I know the Cauſes aſſigned are the baniſhing the <hi>Moors,</hi> and their Numbers buried in the <hi>Weſt-Indies;</hi> but it is plain that that is not the ſole occaſion of the aforeſaid publick Inconvenience: for were there <hi>Arts</hi> and Employments encouraged in their <hi>Country,</hi> as one
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:58535:8"/>Set went out at the Southern Door, another would come in at the <hi>Northern,</hi> and <hi>Europe</hi> would ſupply their Loſs in <hi>America.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It were eaſie to ſhew, How with their own Wool, and ſuch of courſer ſorts, their Neighbours abound with, they might with their own <hi>Manufactories</hi> furniſh their <hi>Weſt Indies,</hi> by which means their Bullion would be their own; which now they are no better than Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Slaves to provide for <hi>Europe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides, if they had <hi>Manufactories,</hi> they would fill their Country with People, and not put them upon a Conſult, as they had in the year 1649, Whether the Court ſhould not remove for the <hi>Indies,</hi> not having People to keep both.</p>
            <p>Add to this, That the want of Employment in <hi>Spain,</hi> occaſions thoſe frequent Acts of Violence, which are committed in that Kingdom; for tho' it is ſo thinly peopled in ſome Parts, that there are ſcarce Men enough to entitle it to the Name of a Country inhabited; yet are there great numbers of <hi>Bandittoes</hi> to ravage upon the few that are there.</p>
            <p>Thus we ſee the diſmal Effects of Idleneſs in <hi>Spain,</hi> which has been of that miſchievous and almoſt fatal Conſequence, as to bring that Kingdom upon the very brink of Ruine; which had before this been devoured by the <hi>French,</hi> had not their other large and induſtrious Dominions preſerved them.</p>
            <p>Having thus taken a ſuccinct and tranſient View of the ill Eſtate of thoſe Kingdoms and People, which are deſtitute of <hi>Arts</hi> and Labour; let us in the ſecond Place, according to our former Method, particularize ſome Inſtances, ſetting forth how Men are obliged to Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in ſome Kingdoms, and the good Effects which reſult from that Engagement.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:58535:8"/>
            <p>In purſuance whereof, I ſhall begin with <hi>Germany,</hi> where we ſhall find a People inferiour to none in their juſt veneration to Antiquity, and due eſtimate of Noble Blood that is truly derived from virtuous and honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Progenitors, which they ſet ſo high a Value upon, as that even to Exceſs they deſpiſe mixing with the <hi>Ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beians;</hi> and yet among theſe great Nobility, the younger of whoſe Families are employed in their Armies, rarely is there found one of them without a <hi>Manual Art;</hi> by which, if reduced to Extremity, he may earn his Bread, rather than live upon the Charity and Benevolence of others, a ſordidneſs of Temper which they bear an utter Abhorrence and Deteſtation to, having too much of that <hi>Roman</hi> Spirit, which had rather loſe a Life, than hold it at the Courteſie of another.</p>
            <p>And this recals into my Memory a Story, which for its pertinent congruity to the preſent Diſcourſe may not be improper to relate: There was about the year 1615 a Nobleman in <hi>Germany,</hi> whoſe Daughter was courted by another Lord, who was a very young Man; when he had made ſuch Progreſs in this Affair, as is uſual by Friends, the old Lord deſired to ſpeak with him, and, after ſome Conference together, asked the young Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, How he intended, if he ſhould marry his Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, to maintain her? He replied, Equal to her Quality. To which the Father returned, That was no Anſwer to his Queſtion; he deſired to know, What he had to maintain her with? To that the younger Lord replyed, He hoped, that was no Queſtion, for that his <hi>Inheritance</hi> was as publick as his Name. The old Lord owned his Poſſeſſions to be great, but asked him if he had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that was ſecurer than Land. The queſtion was ſtrange, but ended in this, That the Father of the young Lady gave his poſitive Reſolve, Never to marry his Daughter, though his Heir, and would have two ſuch
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:58535:9"/>great Eſtates, but unto a Man that had a Manual Trade, by which he might live, if drove from his own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try. This young Lord was Maſter of none at preſent, but rather than loſe his Miſtreſs, he deſired but a years Time, in which he promiſed to acquire one: In order whereunto he got a <hi>Basket-Maker,</hi> the moſt ingenious he could find, and in ſix Months became Maſter of his Trade, with greater Improvement than his Teacher; and as a Proof of his Ingenuity and great Proficiency, in ſo ſmall a Time, he brought to his Miſtreſs a Piece of his Workmanſhip, being a <hi>white Twig Basket;</hi> which for many years after became a general Faſhion among the Ladies by the name of Dreſſing Baskets, brought hither to <hi>England</hi> from <hi>Germany</hi> and <hi>Holland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to compleat the ſurprizingneſs of this Relation, it happened ſome Years after this Nobleman's <hi>Marriage,</hi> that he and his Father in law ſharing in the Misfortunes of the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> were drove naked out of their Eſtates; and in <hi>Holland,</hi> for ſome Years, did this young Lord maintain both his Father-in-law and his own Family, by making <hi>Baskets</hi> of <hi>white Twigs,</hi> to ſuch an unparalell'd Excellency as none could attain: And 'tis from him that they derive thoſe Curioſities that are ſtill made in <hi>Holland</hi> of <hi>Twigwork.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is large a Digreſſion from the Matter in Hand, but the more inſiſted upon, becauſe I deem it not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether improper to my Deſign of ſhewing, How fond and ambitious Men are, in Foreign Countries, of learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Arts</hi> and <hi>Mechanical</hi> Employments, whereby to avoid <hi>Idleneſs,</hi> that common <hi>Peſt</hi> to the Publick Good, and conſequently to every private and individual Intereſt, as involved in the other.</p>
            <p>From this Proſpect of the <hi>Nobility</hi> and <hi>Gentry,</hi> we will now deſcend to a lower View of the meaner and inferior Sort, among them, whoſe Induſtry is ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markably
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:58535:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>great, that even Children of four Years old will earn their Bread: Add to this, That they are kept out of Harm's Way, by the ſame Diverſion, tho' more profitable, whereby we keep our Children in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; and that is by making <hi>wooden Toyes,</hi> painted <hi>Boxes, Pipes,</hi> &amp;c. for our Children to play with: There they employ all the Children of a Town from three Years to eight in thoſe eaſie Matters of ſhaving a little <hi>Stick</hi> of <hi>Fir,</hi> or <hi>dawbing</hi> a little <hi>Paint</hi> upon a <hi>Stick</hi> or <hi>Box;</hi> things of that eaſie nature, as may be done by a Child that can ſpeak, and but hold a Knife, or other ſmall Inſtrument in its Hand.</p>
            <p>When they advance more in Years, 'tis then uſual to pitch upon a Trade; and generally they apply them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to that of their Fathers, whereby you ſhall of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes find 'em to derive their <hi>Pedigree</hi> and their unin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted Succeſſion in the ſame Trade or Employment, in a continued Line from <hi>Father</hi> to <hi>Son,</hi> for ſome Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of Years. And this <hi>Genealogy</hi> as well in <hi>Occupa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> as <hi>Deſcent,</hi> is inſiſted upon by them with as much Pride and Oſtentation as can be ſhewn by their <hi>Nobility,</hi> in their continued Tracings and Derivations of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, from a numerous and antient Stock of their famous and heroical Progenitors.</p>
            <p>'Tis not their Practice, as with us in this Kingdom, to bind an Apprentice for ſeven Years; three or four is their common Standard: and the reaſon is, becauſe they are educated from their Cradle to ſomething of Employment, which renders them the more apt and docible, and conſequently the more capable of attaining to a Ripeneſs and quicker Proficiency in Buſineſs. Whereas our Youth, here in <hi>England,</hi> being bred to nothing before they come to be Apprentices, make a very ſlow Progreſs, and require much longer Time, wherein to reach the Perfection of accompliſhed Artiſts.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:58535:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>And ſuch as are of Families not educated in Mechani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Employments, thoſe they make uſe of, either in Affairs <hi>Military,</hi> or elſe in Studies of gentiler and finer <hi>Arts</hi> than either of theſe; by which admirable decorum, ſo regularly obſerved, in proportioning every Order and Degree of Men among them, to their ſuitable and reſpective Vocations and Capacities, it thence happens, That in whole Provinces there is not a Man that eats the Bread of <hi>Idleneſs,</hi> or of other Men's <hi>Labour</hi> and <hi>Induſtry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay, in the <hi>Hanſ-towns,</hi> they ſtill ſhew a greater Care and ſollicitude in theſe Matters, not judging it expedient to admit of any more than an uſeful and competent num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber for the City, of any who profeſs the liberal Sciences; but, on the contrary, oblige all their Natives and Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants either to <hi>Merchandize, Navigation</hi> or to <hi>Manual Arts</hi> and <hi>Manufactories;</hi> inſomuch that that famous <hi>Mart</hi> of <hi>Hamburgh</hi> (to which <hi>City</hi> belong more Ships of Burthen and Value, for all manner of Trade and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce, than to any City of <hi>Europe, London</hi> and <hi>Amſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> excepted) does admit but of one <hi>Phyſician,</hi> of two <hi>Civilians</hi> for the Law, and but one <hi>Divine,</hi> beſides thoſe which are conſtantly employed in the City: Yet on the contrary Hand, offer great Encouragement to Men of all Nations, to inhabit among them, that are for Mechanick Labour and Sea-Service, as accounting him but a neceſſary Evil, whoſe Induſtry and Parts lye only in the Brain, or bound their Situation in the Head; and one of ſuch they deem ſufficient for thouſands, which work with their Hands.</p>
            <p>By reaſon of which orderly management of Affairs, and the Proviſion made to promote Labour, and to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage <hi>Idleneſs</hi> and all uſeleſs and unactive Men: It is very remarkable, That in this City no Man ever ſaw a <hi>Beggar:</hi> yet many aged and unfortunate Poor there are, occaſioned by Loſſes and croſs Accidents at Sea; but then
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:58535:10"/>ſo Chriſtian and Charitable a Commiſeration of their Condition is entertained by the <hi>Government,</hi> that in all Bargains and Contracts, in that City, ſomething is ſtill preſerved, as a voluntary Gift for the Poor: Or if I may ſo ſay, as a <hi>free-Will Offering</hi> to God for their Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply; and this repoſited in the Hands of the Miniſter of the Pariſh, who has <hi>Church-Wardens</hi> joyned to him, in order to a right Diſpoſal of this Money for the Poor.</p>
            <p>A Ship puts not forth to <hi>Sea,</hi> but with an <hi>Iron Box,</hi> for the uſe of the Poor, of which the Keeper has no Key, but is kept by the <hi>Miniſter</hi> and <hi>Church-Wardens,</hi> and upon the Return of his Voyage, when he receives the <hi>Holy Sacrament</hi> of the Lord's Supper, he brings to the Altar his <hi>Box,</hi> which he uſeth all Care to repleniſh and ſupply; and there is not a Seaman in his Ship but puts ſomething into it, whenever he receives his Wages.</p>
            <p>To what has been already premiſed, 'twould be need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs to name or inſtance to you, the Example of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces,</hi> which are ſo contiguous to our Iſland, as well as juſtly famed throughout the whole Univerſe, for their eminent and induſtrious Improvements, and for ſuch ſuperadditions of <hi>Art</hi> to <hi>Nature,</hi> or rather of ſuch as <hi>Nature</hi> ſeemed not capable of; and which have been of more uſe to them than all their <hi>Martial</hi> Strength, for the Defence of their <hi>Country</hi> againſt their Enemies, and have advanced them from the <hi>poor diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,</hi> to the honourable Title of the <hi>High and Mighty Eſtates of</hi> Holland: And that formerly uſeleſs, and now little Spot of Ground, become the richeſt in <hi>Europe</hi>] is a moſt evident Demonſtration of the miraculous Power of Induſtry, and of thoſe prodigious Acquirements which Human Nature is capable of attaining to, by a laborious and an indefatigable Purſuit; which as it has created a general Eſteem for theſe States throughout the whole World; ſo has reflected no ſmall Diſgrace upon
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:58535:11"/>their Neighbours, whilſt enjoying fertile and profitable Countries, both in their Situation and other abundant National Advantages and Emoluments, far ſuperior to this, they ſuffer their Lands to lie waſte and uncultivated, and neglect all the Opportunities both of <hi>Art</hi> and <hi>Nature,</hi> whereby to enrich and improve them; when on the contrary, theſe are forced to change the very Elements, having more living upon the Water than they have upon the Land; which is ſo plentifully ſtocked, that it ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits of no more.</p>
            <p>If from this little Spot of Ground we paſs farther into the Country, it will be worth our while to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, What Care and Diligence is uſed by the <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> to oblige the Rural unto Works, for the Publick Good.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Flanders</hi> they admit not a young Man to enter into the State of Marriage, without firſt obtaining a Certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate from the Magiſtrate of the Place of his Reſidence and abode, ſetting forth, His having <hi>planted</hi> ſuch a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of <hi>Trees,</hi> &amp;c. I might demonſtrate the Truth of this Point to you, from a great variety of other Inſtances, both of Countries and Perſons, which would be agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and pertinent enough to my preſent Deſign, but aiming at Brevity, this may ſuffice to ſhew the great Care and laudable Endeavours of <hi>Foreign Governments,</hi> to oblige their People to Labour and Induſtry; and to evince this Nation of that wonderful Succeſs it has met with, for the Growth and Improvement of their reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Inhabitants in Riches and the like proſperous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingences of this Life.</p>
            <p>I come now, in the third Place, to demonſtrate with what poſſibility and good Succeſs, the ſame Induſtry might be effected, and conſequently become <hi>practicable</hi> in theſe Kingdoms, which is uſed in others, and how the want of it leads to the ſame <hi>Fate,</hi> which became de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:58535:11"/>of thoſe <hi>Monarchies</hi> and <hi>Countries</hi> already men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned.</p>
            <p>We are not ignorant, That Chriſtianity in general, and more eſpecially as profeſſed in its antient Purity in this Nation, does indiſpenſably oblige all its <hi>Votaries</hi> and Adherents to a ſober and laborious courſe of Life. We know, by the Parable of the Talents, in the Goſpel, That we muſt increaſe both our Spiritual and Temporal Enjoyments; that both a Stock of Grace and of worldly Comforts and Accommodations, are to be improved by our Labour and Induſtry, tho' it's true our Care and Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitude for the laſt, muſt be ſubordinate to the firſt; yet however, as we are but <hi>Stewards</hi> to what we enjoy, we muſt ſo <hi>manage,</hi> as to be capable of giving a good <hi>Account;</hi> and as we are but Servants, entruſted with an induſtrious laying out of theſe Advantages of human Life, we muſt ſo husband and improve them too, as to be able to return them with an Increaſe (the effects of our Labour and Vigilance) when our Grand Maſter ſhall require them at our Hands. And indeed the inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of the whole Creation, is in all its parts ſo fitly accommodated to, and ſo naturally capable of Labour and Induſtry, that tho' Man in his firſt Eſtate was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted from, yet now muſt bear a conſiderable ſhare in this general Pains and Toil of the World. The very inanimate Creatures, the Sun, Moon and Stars, have in their kinds their proper and diſtinct Offices of Labor, to which they were firſt deſigned by Sovereign Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and which they duly and regularly perform. The Trees and Plants, and things of a <hi>Vegetative Nature,</hi> diſcharge their ſeveral Functions, in concurrence with this grand Deſign. What Slavery and Toil is undergone by <hi>Senſitive Creatures,</hi> how they labour and are haraſſed with continual Pains, needs not be illuſtrated. In the Order of the Creation, the next Degree above theſe are
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:58535:12"/>Men, which by reaſon of their <hi>Superiour Faculties</hi> incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municable to <hi>Senſitive Beings;</hi> we call <hi>Rational Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</hi> But to paſs by them at preſent, if we look up unto a higher <hi>Species</hi> or Rank of <hi>Creatures,</hi> the <hi>Angelical Beings,</hi> we ſhall find that thoſe <hi>Bleſſed Spirits</hi> are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually buſied and employed either in repeated <hi>Halle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lujahs</hi> and <hi>Euchariſtical Praiſes;</hi> or elſe are ſent upon fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent <hi>Embaſſies</hi> and <hi>Negotiations</hi> into this lower World; or admitting the Speculation of their <hi>Tutelary</hi> Function, are many of them obliged to a conſtant Warchfulneſs, and an immediate Attendance upon Man, whereby to oppoſe and repel the Temptations of <hi>Satan</hi> and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate <hi>Legions,</hi> by inſtilling into their Hearts a Love and Veneration of the Divine Nature, and by ſtriking them with an awful Dread of, and a moſt ſubmiſſive Regard to his Sovereign and Imperial Majeſty, and conſequently by impreſſing deep <hi>Characters</hi> of <hi>Religion,</hi> and the Fear of God upon their Souls. It remains then, That of that great variety of <hi>Creatures</hi> which God made, all, in their diſtinct Conditions and Capacities, are naturally ſubjected to <hi>Labour</hi> and Induſtry: ſhall then man be excepted, who was made but a little lower than the <hi>Angels,</hi> and conſequently in a ſuperior degree to all other created Beings, endowed with thoſe excellent Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties of <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Judgment,</hi> of which brute and ſenſitive <hi>Creatures</hi> do not participate, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are not ſo qualified for a right management of <hi>Labour</hi> as Men are? for tho' many of them exceed man in Strength, whereby they become in the greateſt <hi>Toil</hi> more indefatigable than they; yet for want of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the <hi>diſcourſive</hi> or <hi>rational Faculty,</hi> cannot direct their <hi>Pains</hi> to proper and advantagious Ends and Uſes; but in this are ordered and governed by Man, as they are the Inſtruments which God and Nature has appointed to be uſeful and ſubſervient to him, in the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:58535:12"/>promoting of <hi>Labour</hi> and Induſtry. Seeing then that Man is thus eminently qualified beyond all the other Beings of this lower Orb for great and laborious Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provements; it follows neceſſarily, that he muſt either act agreeably to theſe peculiar Excellencies of Human Nature, or elſe ſink himſelf below the Condition of Brutes and the moſt inferior Beings, who (as is alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy proved) do by natural Inſtinct carry a direct Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence to their firſt Inſtitution in this reſpect. But to paſs from a Religious to a Natural Conſideration: If we conſider that Nature aims at an exact Symmetry and Proportion in all things, and does as much purſue a conſtant Order and Harmony in all her Operations, as ſhe carefully declines Irregularity and Confuſion; we muſt then needs acknowledg, That that which we look upon as a Deformity or a ſuperfluous Excreſcence in a Body <hi>Natural,</hi> muſt in a parallel Proportion be juſtly reckoned to be ſo in a Body <hi>Politick:</hi> And if it be ſo, then tho' we muſt confeſs the Fingers to be the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Hand; yet one more than of uſe is vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garly ſtyled a <hi>monſtrous</hi> Production (tho more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly a <hi>deviation</hi> of Nature from her Intention of <hi>Order</hi>) Why then may it not be with a Parity of Reaſon ſo thought of an uſeleſs Man, in a <hi>State</hi> or <hi>Commonwealth;</hi> ſuch a one being not only a Deformity, but a Nuiſance unto it, as well as a Blemiſh to, as an Excreſcence in, any <hi>Government.</hi> That which takes away the <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Sap</hi> from the <hi>Root</hi> of the <hi>State,</hi> but neither imparts any to it, nor produceth any <hi>Fruit,</hi> and therefore muſt either be ſo cultivated and diſciplin'd by good Laws and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſo as to make it Fertile, or elſe deſerves no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Uſage than that of being cut down, for why cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breth it the Ground?</p>
            <p>But I muſt beg Pardon for this tedious Harangue, upon theſe two Arguments drawn from <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Nature,</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:58535:13"/>obliging Men to Labour and Induſtry; and proceed to ſhew, How what has been premiſed may be calcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated to the <hi>Meridian</hi> of, and applicable enough to this <hi>Nation:</hi> For the proof whereof, That <hi>England</hi> exceeds any part of <hi>Europe</hi> for the Advantage of its Situation and its Utenſils of Trade and Commerce, is a matter of ſo unqueſtionable a Nature as none will diſpute, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that they can want Vent for their Labours, ſince it is a Spot of Ground, which ſo many of other Countries muſt neceſſarily paſs by: All the Miſchief that attends it is its Eaſe and Plenty, and that the Proviſion for a Day requires not the Labour of half an one in many Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>Now if it be a Matter of ſo great Facility to purchaſe a Livelihood, it ſeems to be a Crime of an higher <hi>Aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,</hi> to live upon the Labour of others.</p>
            <p>But the common Plea of <hi>Idlers</hi> is, That they would work if any would employ them; which ſeems to charge the Government with omiſſion, in not providing Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments for all Ages and Sexes, as to which the Laws already made (we ſee) do not, tho' in ſome Parts of the Kingdom, where the woollen Manufactory is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable, the common ſort are ſo taken care of, that they are no Trouble or Charge to the Pariſh: But then paſs to other Parts of the Kingdom, and you ſhall find num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers a Burthen both to themſelves and others.</p>
            <p>It is a Matter then that deſerves our Conſideration, What <hi>Vocations</hi> and Employments every Part of the Kingdom is moſt fit and proper for; and where there is not Employment in <hi>Manufactories,</hi> if it be by the Sea, to employ them in <hi>fiſhing</hi> or <hi>Navigation;</hi> or if they take not to either of theſe, and their own Country affords them not other Employments, that then they ſhould be removed to other parts of the Kingdom; by which courſe they would not remain idle at Home. And why may
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:58535:13"/>not this be as <hi>practicable</hi> at large, and in the whole, as at this day it is in part in ſome places of the Kingdom; as for inſtance, in the <hi>Manufactory</hi> part of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> where the <hi>Church-wardens</hi> and <hi>Overſeers</hi> of the <hi>Poor</hi> viſit their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors Houſes, and where they find any Children above ten years of age, not kept to ſome Trade or Employment, they take them from their <hi>Parents,</hi> and put them to ſome.</p>
            <p>Now, if this be done to the <hi>Poor,</hi> why may it not be ſo to the <hi>Rich?</hi> I know it will be anſwer'd, That the reaſon is not the ſame; for, ſay they, One is to prevent a charge to the Pariſh, that of the <hi>Poor,</hi> which cannot be feared of the other, the <hi>Rich.</hi> But there have been ſome Inſtances of that too; beſides that, Gentlemens Children are often not only a Charge, but alſo Enemies to the Kingdom: And, Why ſhould not this publick Inconvenience be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided againſt, of which we have but too frequent and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable Examples at the <hi>Bar</hi> and the <hi>Gallows?</hi> How many Hundreds in the year are taken off by the hands of Juſtice, that might have been uſeful Members in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, if they had been taken care of, and been thus edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated in their Youth? It is a ſtrange piece of Gentility, that looks upon it as an Invaſion upon its Priviledges, if put to a Trade, and will rather ſubmit to an <hi>Halter</hi> than <hi>Indentures.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, where an evil <hi>Cuſtom</hi> is become hereditary and predominant, a <hi>Law</hi> is needful to cut off the Entail.</p>
            <p>The Glory of a Kingdom is Men and Money; <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> hath, in a competent proportion, the Bleſſing of both, but might be improved to more than double. For at the moſt moderate computation, it is not half Peopled; and ſince there is ſo much wanting in number, the beſt way to ſupply that deficiency; is, by <hi>Induſtry,</hi> which would not only encreaſe the Treaſure of the Kingdom, but that which is the more valuable Treaſure, Men. 'Tis a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter as well of Experience as Lamentation, That want of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:58535:14"/>Employments puts Men upon looſe and unwarrantable actions: Idleneſs muſt be fed, and Luxury indulg'd, and Pride maintain'd; and Gentility ſupported; and when Profuſeneſs has eaten up the <hi>hereditary</hi> Subſtance, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly where there was but little at firſt, as moſt commonly it is in <hi>younger Brothers,</hi> then the <hi>Padding Trade,</hi> and the gentile way of taking a Purſe, is generally the <hi>Prologue</hi> to the ſucceeding <hi>Tragedy,</hi> whoſe <hi>Scenes</hi> are as diſmal as they are common. Now, if ſuch idle Extravagants as theſe cannot maintain themſelves ſingly, without running into theſe violent courſes, which end in their deſtruction, they can much leſs provide for a Family.</p>
            <p>And therefore, if a Statute were made, That no Child under Three hundred pounds <hi>per annum,</hi> ſhould be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted longer at School, than to the Fifteenth year of his Age: but then, if his <hi>Parents</hi> or <hi>Guardian</hi> did not, he ſhould be put to ſome Trade or Employment, there would be leſs work for the <hi>Executioner,</hi> and more for the <hi>Cook;</hi> and probable it is, that in Twenty years there would be a greater number of People than in Fifty be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
            <p>'Tis not poſſible, in ſo narrow a compaſs as this Tract, to ſet down the methods that muſt be us'd in ſuch an al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration as this would produce. I ſhall only anſwer two <hi>popular</hi> Objections, which ſeem to lie oppoſite to a general Reformation in that Latitude wherein I have propos'd it. The firſt is this,</p>
            <p>That if none under Three hundred pounds <hi>per annum,</hi> were admitted to apply themſelves to <hi>Learning,</hi> and to a ſtudy of the <hi>Liberal Sciences;</hi> this would be lookt upon as an act of great ſeverity, and a very unreaſonable limitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſuch whoſe natural <hi>genius</hi> and capacity might enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle them to a very great proficiency in Learning, and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:58535:14"/>conſequently to very eminent Stations both in <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> and yet come not under any ſuch qualify'd degree of Fortune or yearly Subſtance. This, ſay ſome, would be a great obſtruction and diſcouragement to <hi>Learning,</hi> which it is as well the Ornament as Intereſt of every Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to promote, and which we want not Inſtances of ſome great <hi>Patrons</hi> in this kind, who were men of mean <hi>Birth,</hi> and of an inferiour Fortune in the World. To which I anſwer, That the Limitation inſiſted upon, in the method propos'd, would occaſion no want or decay of <hi>Learning</hi> of any, much leſs of all ſorts, where there are ſo many Thouſands that will come under the Qualification of having Three hundred pounds <hi>per annum,</hi> or Money to purchaſe it.</p>
            <p>Again, That it would be an Act of Severity and an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable Limitation upon ſuch who could not come up to that Qualification, and for that reaſon be excluded from Study, notwithſtanding that their Ingenuity ſeem'd to animate them with hopes of attaining to no contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptible degree in it.</p>
            <p>To this it may be reply'd, That if there appears much more Prejudice to the Kingdom in general, by admitting of ſuch, than the loſs will be to every particular Perſon in this Caſe; then, I preſume, a private Prejudice is much more reaſonable than a publick; and ſome particular In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniencies are to be born and conniv'd at, when the removal of them is incompatible with the common Good and general Intereſt of the State.</p>
            <p>That the Sons of divers very ordinary perſons have ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived to an eminent height of Learning and Parts, and have become very great Scholars in all kinds of Litera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, is a truth too undeniable to be diſputed: and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, by how much they have by their Studies advaneed themſelves from a low and deſpicable eſtate, to an high degree, and to an eminent figure in the World; by ſo
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:58535:15"/>much are they juſtly to be accounted the more honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and do accordingly deſerve our greateſt reſpect; for Honour (as the Moraliſts ſpeak) is founded upon Virtue, and 'tis that alone which merits Honour. And, indeed I muſt needs account thoſe men to be much the more honourable, and conſequently to merit a greater ſhare in our Eſteem; who raiſe themſelves by their own acquiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Virtue and Induſtry, from a <hi>Plebeian</hi> or vulgar ſtate, to ſome eminent poſt or ſtation; than thoſe are, who derive their perſons from <hi>Heroical Anceſtors,</hi> in a long and uninterrupted Line of Succeſſion; but baſely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate from thoſe Actions and virtuous Atchievements which were the firſt ennobled the Blood of their Predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors.</p>
            <p>Theſe laſt ſeem as great a reproach and infamy, as the others are a credit, both to themſelves and their Progeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors. But then we muſt conſider, that though there may and have been ſome ſuch rare men among the vulgar, yet there are Hundreds for One, which every year produces of the ſame Fund, who come abroad into the <hi>world,</hi> like <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rach</hi>'s <hi>Frogs,</hi> that only <hi>croak,</hi> and make a <hi>noiſe</hi> in the <hi>Country,</hi> and not finding Preferment, either for want of Intereſt or Abilities, or both, become, inſtead of an Ornament or Help, a Diſgrace and a Nuiſance to the Kingdom; nay, and not ſeldom create publick Diſturbances, and often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times make dangerous Concuſſions both in Church and State. For, Who are generally the <hi>Authors</hi> of Schiſms and Factions in the Church? Who of Mutinies and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions in the State, but ſuch <hi>Malecontents,</hi> whoſe igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, or other contemptible circumſtances, debar them from any conſiderable ſhare in either? and then what their Parts or virtuous Endowments cannot compaſs, their Malice and inveteracy does commonly endeavour to deſtroy. Were it not for this, we ſhould not ſee ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny heterodox Profeſſors of Divinity, ſo many <hi>Enthu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſms,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:58535:15"/>Errors</hi> and <hi>Hereſies</hi> in Religion; not ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Mountebanks, Quacks,</hi> and <hi>Empericks</hi> in Phyſick; not ſo many <hi>Pettifoggers</hi> and ignorant <hi>Barreters</hi> in the Law; and to compleat theſe <hi>Legions,</hi> Who are the men they call <hi>Sharpers,</hi> but generally ſuch whoſe ignorant Parents ambition is to make Gentlemen by educating them Beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gars? for, perhaps not one of ten is able to do more than to ſend his Son to the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity,</hi> and there he muſt ſhift for himſelf, and oftentimes, for want of a competency to ſubſiſt upon, is forc'd to come down into the Country by the next Carrier, and ſpend the greateſt part of his time there in ſolitude and want of converſation: and unleſs he can become a Philoſopher by Inſpiration, or by a Sympa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thetick Influence be inſtructed in all the Learning of the Univerſity, at an hundred miles diſtance from it, 'tis an hundred to one but, at the ſeven years end, he is become <hi>Retrograde,</hi> and has ſcarce ſo good a ſtock of Learning, as when he commenc'd a Freſh man. And is not this man like to make a very eminent <hi>Doctor</hi> in the Church, or an able and accompliſh'd <hi>Politician</hi> in the State.</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſe that one of theſe poor men can maintain his Son in the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity,</hi> till he arrives to the degree of a <hi>Batchellor,</hi> or perhaps a <hi>Maſter of Arts;</hi> yet upon his lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Colledge, he comes abroad in neceſſity; which oftentimes puts him upon evil and prepoſterous courſes, whereby to provide for himſelf. Now were it not infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely more conducive to the Good of the State, to want one man of Learning from the Mechanicks, ſuppoſe him never ſo excellent, than to have an hundred that prove Vermin, and are deſtructive, inſtead of one, or ſay a few more, that may become active and ſerviceable <hi>Members</hi> to the Common wealth.</p>
            <p>Beſides, there is ſcope enough for thoſe of the Vulgar, that are of a pregnant ingenuity, to employ it in the fineſt <hi>Arts</hi> and moſt curious ſort of Induſtry and Labour,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:58535:16"/>wherein they may not only arrive to great eminency, but become more profitable Inſtruments to the Good of the Kingdom, than they can hope to be by their Learning, of which we have no preſent Proſpect of any want, but may be thought to ſtand upon equal, if not ſuperiour, terms with any part of the Univerſe.</p>
            <p>But then, 'tis more than manifeſt, That we are ſo far from diſputing the <hi>Priority</hi> above, that we come infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhort of other <hi>Countries</hi> in our Mechanicks and finer Arts, which ſeem to be a proper Province for the middle People of this Kingdom to be engag'd in, leaving the ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of humane Literature to thoſe who are able to maintain themſelves, if by an adverſe <hi>genius,</hi> or other obſtacles and contingences, they ſhould happen to miſcarry in it.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Obligation will be, That if we educate all Gentlemens Sons unto <hi>Trades,</hi> it will hinder the Nation from Martial Improvements, and ſo be reduc'd to a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of employing Foreigners in the greateſt Places of Truſt in the Army.</p>
            <p>In anſwer to which, we muſt conſider, That ſuch of the <hi>younger Brothers</hi> as are addicted to <hi>War,</hi> may be ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inſtated in that Employment, and ſo may be reaſonably accounted, as if actually converſant in Trades; and ſuch as ſhall affect the <hi>Seas,</hi> may be bred up in <hi>Navigation;</hi> Of which we have Examples near home, particularly the <hi>French King,</hi> who breeds up Gentlemen and others in this manner, at his own Charge.</p>
            <p>But it may perhaps, though with no ſemblance of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, be urg'd, That looſe and indigent Youth are in ſome reſpects needful in the Commonwealth, for private Souldiers, which would be wanting, if all men were bred to <hi>Trades.</hi> But daily Experience ſhews, That numbers who are put out to <hi>Trades</hi> prove <hi>idle</hi> and <hi>extravagant;</hi> and of ſuch there is a greater proportion in the Kingdom than would compoſe an Army.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:58535:16"/>
            <p>So that if this method were purſu'd, of putting all the Youth of the Nation upon ſome Employment or other, this ſignal Advantage would accrew from it: That whereas now Armies are ſupplied out of the Vagrants, and Refuſe of the Kingdom they would then be made up of a better ſort of men, tho' yet ſo extravagant, as to be impatient under <hi>ſober Confinement</hi> and <hi>daily Labour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By what we have hitherto diſcours'd and inſiſted upon, it is ſufficiently apparent, That the uſe of <hi>Trades</hi> and of <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanick Arts</hi> are more commodious for the State, than the educating the poorer ſort in <hi>Learning</hi> and the <hi>Sciences:</hi> And, if this be plain, it cannot then be denied, That there is more reaſon to bring up thoſe that are neceſſitous, in <hi>Mechanical</hi> or other Occupations.</p>
            <p>The next thing to be conſider'd, are the great Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages that will ariſe to the Kingdom in general, by keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all hands at work, and theſe are numerous, the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal of which are reduceable to the following Heads.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> It will, in ſome proportion, be an occaſion of bringing in new <hi>Colonies,</hi> and of encreaſing the number of our own. We are now ſupplied from <hi>foreign parts</hi> with divers Commodities, which, if the Kingdom were reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with <hi>Artizans,</hi> they would furniſh us with here at home: For, Pray what is it which makes the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces</hi> ſo full of Commodities of their own Arts and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufactories, which they tranſport to all parts of the World, but that every one there is bred to ſome Trade, and ſo are forced to rack their Inventions to obtain a live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihood? And, notwithſtanding that they abound with ſo many People, as would with us be accounted a Burthen, yet there is ſtill encouragement given out of the Publick Stock for any Foreigners or Fugitives, that are <hi>Artizans,</hi> to live among them. Of this we have Inſtances recent among our ſelves, of the many Hundreds that abandoned this Kingdom, upon the Reſtauration of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, and had Houſes free to ſettle in.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:58535:17"/>
            <p>Now as this employing of all ſorts of People would increaſe the Strength of the Kingdom by its numbers; ſo would it alſo as well the Riches and Stock of it, by its Treaſure (every <hi>Bee</hi> adds ſome <hi>Hone<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> to he <hi>Hive</hi>) and at the ſame Time would eaſe every individual Man from a great part of the Taxes which now he lies under.</p>
            <p>It would alſo disburthen the Kingdom from <hi>Beggars,</hi> that by their Multitudes are become the Shame and the Plague of the Nation, whoſe Children are begot, and ſo bred up in the Trade of Begging, as if they were em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bodied into a <hi>Society,</hi> and eſtabliſhed by a Law.</p>
            <p>Not that I deſign to diſcourage here that admirable Virtue of <hi>Alms-giving<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> which is certainly a moſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian and Divine Grace, when duly placed and regularly and prudently diſpenſed, and which the Law both of God and Nature require from us; and which is not only the beſt way, to cauſe God to ſhowre down upon us his Divine Favours in an immenſe affluence of temperal Bleſſings; but alſo to lay up heavenly Treaſures and everlaſting Proviſions for us, in the immortally Divine State in the other World. It remains then both as our Duty and Intereſt, that we act agreeably to the <hi>Infallible Author</hi>'s Direction, in this Caſe <hi>(viz.) Thou ſhalt take Care for thy poor;</hi> but then the Queſtion is how, and in what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, this ought to be performed? for the ſame <hi>infallible Author</hi> alſo tells us, That there was no Beggar in <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And indeed tho' <hi>Charity</hi> be as well the Duty as Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> as has been already touched upon, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing that it be diſpenſed in a fit and regular manner; yet on the other Hand, it is a barbarous Cruelty, becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing none but the <hi>Sons</hi> of it, the <hi>Emiſſaries</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribute <hi>Charity</hi> to common <hi>Beggars.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is rather Chriſtian Compaſſion to prevent it; and indeed it is no ſmall matter of Wonder, that <hi>Good</hi> ſhould be ſo often faulty in this reſpect, and that our <hi>Divines</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:58535:17"/>(with reverence to their Order I ſpeak it) ſhould ſo much preach up Charity in general, and yet ſeem many of them to omit the weightieſt part of it, namely, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion for the Souls of thoſe poor Creatures that beg for Bread to ſupport this Life; but neither themſelves nor o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers take thought or are ſolicitous for the Life to come. If ſuch, whoſe ſacred Function does immediately oblige them to the <hi>Cure of Souls,</hi> would (I ſay not all, but at leaſt ſome of them) more ſeriouſly weigh and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this Point, many of our <hi>Pulpits</hi> would not be ſo ſtill and unconcerned, upon this Subject, as they appear to be. By our prepoſterous diſtributing of Charity, we ſeem to invert that of the <hi>Apoſtle, Not many mighty,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>but the poor of this world are choſen.</hi> In this Kingdom it is quite otherwiſe, for we take only the ſame Care of them that we do of Brutes, to prevent their ſtarving, but alaſs have too ſmall a regard of what becomes of their Souls.</p>
            <p>Now there can be no effectual way of doing this, but by laying a good Foundation, in taking up the <hi>younger ſort,</hi> and putting them to <hi>Trades;</hi> and as for the <hi>Elder</hi> and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crepit,</hi> that are capable of no Employment, ſuch to be maintained by the Pariſh, but ſo as to have no liberty for Begging; and the Effects of this will be, That there will hardly be any aged or decrepit Poor, moſt of which are made ſo, either by Fraud and Deſign of <hi>Vagrants</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, or by being the Children of ſuch, and ſo for want of Care or Attendance, are become deform'd or maim'd.</p>
            <p>It is alſo remarkable, That <hi>Mechanicks</hi> prevent <hi>Famin</hi> in a Nation; this at firſt ſight will appear a <hi>Paradox,</hi> that the multiplying of <hi>Mouths,</hi> that eat <hi>Corn,</hi> whoſe Hands <hi>ſow</hi> none, ſhould yet increaſe <hi>Food;</hi> which Matter of Fact demonſtrates the Truth of, notwithſtanding: For who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſaw a <hi>Famin</hi> in <hi>Holland?</hi> on the contrary, they who <hi>ſow</hi> none, yet ſupply other parts of the World with <hi>Corn,</hi> which they effect by means of their <hi>Arts</hi> and <hi>Trade,</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:58535:18"/>which drives the more profitable <hi>Plough</hi> of the two, that of the <hi>Sea.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is obſerved, That no places are more frequently afflicted with <hi>Famin,</hi> than thoſe Countries which are employed in <hi>Tillage;</hi> and the reaſon of this Scarcity is very plain. For if their <hi>Corn</hi> fail, they have no other way whereby to ſupply their Want; but it is otherwiſe with thoſe who depend upon <hi>Arts</hi> and <hi>Trade,</hi> for the extent of their <hi>Harveſt reaches</hi> the utmoſt Confines of the <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> if not known World; and if one Place fails, they can eaſily have recourſe to another.</p>
            <p>Again, <hi>Labour</hi> and <hi>Arts</hi> are a means to purchaſe to us one of the greateſt Bleſſings of this World, length of Daies; for it both prolongs Life and prevents untimely Death: And for the proof of the firſt of theſe, it is obſerved, as a Matter of common Experience, That there are more old Men who from their Infancy have been employed in Labour and Trades, than there are of Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men; which is agreeable to what the <hi>Phyſicians</hi> affirm with a great deal of Reaſon and Truth, That the Work of the Body is not ſo deſtructive of, nor decaies not the Vitals ſo much as the <hi>Study</hi> and Labour of the Head, or the Intemperance of the Appetite, which Men who conſult their Eaſe, and ſenſual Complacencies, are too too apt to indulge.</p>
            <p>And in the ſecond Place, That they prevent untimely Death, is a Truth ſo undeniable as needs no Arguments to confirm it, every Daies Experience ſufficiently evin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing it unto us, That when Youth are educated in the way and courſe of Buſineſs, their Heads are employed as well as their Hands; which leaves no room for vitious Plots and Deſigns, nor for pinching Neceſſity to enforce their breaking through the Laws of God and Man, to make Proviſion for thoſe Luſts and Exorbitances, that at laſt bring them to the <hi>Gibbet.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:58535:18"/>
            <p>I now come to the laſt part of this Diſcourſe, to ſhew the Miſchiefs that attend, and 'tis reaſonably to be feared, will fall upon this Kingdom, for the want of a good and regular Diſcipline, in the Manners and Lives of the People.</p>
            <p>I ſhall begin with thoſe ill Effects and Conſequences which <hi>Idleneſs</hi> produces in <hi>Religion.</hi> It is the Care of moſt <hi>Parents</hi> to educate their <hi>Children</hi> in ſome Religion or other, of whatever Shape or diſtinct Profeſſion it be entituled to; for he may be reaſonably accounted a Monſter in Nature, and a common Enemy to Humanity, that profeſſes the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Religion himſelf, and could patiently ſuffer his Child to be bred up in <hi>Mahometaniſm:</hi> yet perhaps we want not thouſands who do worſe than this, it being eaſier to convert and proſelyte a Man to <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> that believes a <hi>Deity,</hi> but is zealous in his erroneous Apprehenſions of his Divine Nature and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; than to peſwade one to embrace the Faith, who denies that prime and received Principle of the Exiſtence of a God, and conſequently diſowns all the ſubordinate Tenets and Articles of Religion. Now alas too many there are of this Kind, whoſe Parents bring them up without Trades, and conſequently having no Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, will naturally have recourſe to thoſe which are Vitious and Unlawful, which the evil Spirit that acts them will be ſure not to be deficient in ſupplying them with an abundant variety of, as being conſcious of the hazard he incurs of loſing them, if he affords them lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure for ſerious Thoughts and Reflections.</p>
            <p>And as men bred up to no <hi>Trade</hi> or Employments have rarely any <hi>Religion,</hi> ſo neither are they demeanable to the Laws of the Land, to which Religion is the moſt laſting and ſureſt Tye or Obligation; and ſubordinately to that Buſineſs and Employment have the next prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Force with them: for theſe naturally beget a <hi>Property</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:58535:19"/>which requires <hi>Protection</hi> and Security by the law; whereas he that hath nothing to loſe, nor endeavors to acquire any thing but by a manifeſt Violation and Infring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Laws, his ſiniſter Intereſts are ſuch as ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly encline him to deſtroy them.</p>
            <p>Hence it is that we frequently find, That Men of no <hi>Buſineſs</hi> are and have been the publick Diſturbers and <hi>Incendiaries</hi> of a Nation; no Plots or Rebellions are brought upon the <hi>Stage,</hi> but are managed and projected by this ſort of Men, who are the moſt conſiderable Party among the <hi>Actors,</hi> who take no greater Pleaſure in any thing than in <hi>fiſhing</hi> in <hi>troubled Waters,</hi> by which means they not only become deſtructive to themſelves, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lure and entice others, inveigling and drawing in thoſe (that are in a way of Trade and Buſineſs) to their Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous and evil Practices, to the irreverſible Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of many Families.</p>
            <p>And as they thus ruin divers in their <hi>Eſtates,</hi> ſo alſo in their <hi>Lives.</hi> It is a Subject of great Grief and Lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, to conſider what Numbers are every year brought to violent Deaths by the Hand of the <hi>Executioner;</hi> and yet more numerous they are, by much, who deſtroy themſelves by <hi>Debauchery</hi> and <hi>Intemperance:</hi> ſo that it may be ſaid by by a moderate Computation, That as the <hi>Sword</hi> of <hi>Juſtice</hi> hath <hi>ſlain its thouſands;</hi> ſo a complica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Diſeaſes contracted by <hi>idle</hi> and <hi>looſe</hi> Men, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Employments, <hi>have ſlain their ten thouſands.</hi> And to ſum up all, theſe are the Men that in the preſent Juncture of Affairs, are the Plague and Peſt of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that as <hi>Locuſts</hi> ſwarm in all Places, echoing out the moſt extravagant <hi>Panegyricks</hi> upon their Defender, the <hi>abdicated</hi> King; they go by the Name of <hi>Sharpers</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> and are ſo formidable a Body that none dares oppoſe their aſſaulting any that aſſume to contradict them, in magnifying their Protector the late King; for
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:58535:19"/>of ſuch indeed are his Party and Adherents compoſed, whoſe Actions carry an agreeable Reſemblance as well to the preſent <hi>Principles</hi> as known <hi>Practices</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome;</hi> there being not any Profeſſion in the World, that allows of or connives at and indulges <hi>Idleneſs</hi> in an equal degree to the Papiſts.</p>
            <p>For as <hi>Ignorance</hi> is the <hi>Mother</hi> of their <hi>Devotion,</hi> ſo is <hi>Idleneſs</hi> the Nurſe of it, as is obſerveable in their rude and implicit <hi>Votaries</hi> in <hi>Ireland:</hi> in which Kingdom 'tis uſual with them, at Maſs, to make publick Collections for a <hi>Thief</hi> or <hi>Idler;</hi> but if a conſtant <hi>labouring Man,</hi> that ſpent not his Time with them in Drinking and idleneſs, be by Misfortune reduced to Poverty, they will give no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to ſuch a Man, but ſay, he was a <hi>Churle,</hi> that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was Good, but was always making for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</p>
            <p>And it is to be remark'd, that there was never ſo many <hi>Stone-Weavers</hi> (as the <hi>Dutch</hi> call idle men) ſeen in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> as in the few years of the late King <hi>James,</hi> ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fligate wretches being the apteſt Inſtruments for the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of the Eſtabliſh'd Laws and the Religion of the Nation, and the introduction of <hi>Popery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It belongs not to me to aſſume the preſcribing of Laws and Methods, whereby to redreſs theſe publick Evils and Inconveniencies too predominant in the State, and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent greater, that ſeem to be imminent over, and dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly to threaten this Kingdom, by theſe infinite ſwarms of <hi>Waſps,</hi> which act the part of <hi>ſluggiſh Drones,</hi> in living upon the <hi>labour</hi> of others, but are but too induſtrious to do miſchief, and too ready to embrace every occaſion, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to put the whole Kingdom into a flame and a general combuſtion.</p>
            <p>However, there ſeems to be a poſſibility, at leaſt, to leſſen this growing Evil, and yet not by the uſual way of driving theſe <hi>Malecontents</hi> and <hi>bad Members</hi> out of the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:58535:20"/>Nation; <hi>a Remedy worſe than the Diſeaſe,</hi> which in another Diſcourſe may be proved. But the more profitable way ſeems to take them all up, and ſuch of them as are young, to diſpoſe of to ſuch Trades and Employments as are moſt ſuitable to their natural <hi>Genius</hi>'s and <hi>Capacities,</hi> and to ſupply the want of Money uſually given with <hi>Apprentices,</hi> to inlarge the time of their Service.</p>
            <p>For the other ſorts, which are either Gentlemens <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi> or elſe ſuch as pretend to be ſo, becauſe educated to no Employments, and are become <hi>Sharpers,</hi> and live by <hi>Cheating</hi> and <hi>Gaming.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the firſt of theſe there ſeems to be a commiſerating and a compaſſionate ſenſe of their quality and condition, due from the Government, and equally to their <hi>Birth,</hi> they ſhould be preferr'd in <hi>Civil</hi> and <hi>Military</hi> Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which perhaps they would have long ſince taken up, but had not Money to purchaſe; a ſin now become <hi>bare-fac'd,</hi> and ought to be univerſally exploded by all Mankind; for, 'tis the <hi>Peſtilence</hi> that walks in <hi>darkneſs,</hi> and ruins the Kingdom by a double Miſchief. Firſt, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructs the Preferment of Gentlemen, and of Perſons of worth, and in conſequence to that misfortune, puts them upon lewd and extravagant courſes, whereby to ſupply their preſent neceſſity: And then in the ſecond place, fills up Vacancies with ſuch men, whoſe <hi>Gold,</hi> not <hi>Parts,</hi> entitle them thereunto.</p>
            <p>The other ſet or ſort of men, are the <hi>Sharpers,</hi> who by the Iniquity of the Times are become a <hi>Fraternity</hi> almoſt too great for the <hi>Civil Magiſtrate</hi> to manage or correct. I will not preſume to determine which is the greater Evil, hanging for <hi>Felony,</hi> or letting thoſe eſcape that are juſtly to be deem'd the greater Offenders; but ſure I am, that the law is wanting to them, and may well be ſo, theſe being a Diſeaſe newly ſprung up in the Kingdom, and therefore as yet there is no Law made or provided, as a proper <hi>Antidote</hi> againſt it.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:58535:20"/>
            <p>Now, for theſe <hi>Sparks</hi> who are become thus rampant amongſt us, What Remedy can be preſcrib'd more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducive to the Good of the State, than to exchange them for honeſt men, that were taken upon their lawful Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments at Sea by the <hi>Turks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This, I foreſee, will not eſcape a ſevere cenſure; I muſt therefore beg leave to offer ſuch Reaſons as have induced me to be of this opinion; in the proſecution whereof, I perceive that it will be urg'd, That it is a juſt Law to hang <hi>Felons</hi> and <hi>Robbers.</hi> But, Would it not, I pray, be a mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Puniſhment to exchange ſuch Offenders, for honeſt men that are in Slavery?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again,</hi> Theſe <hi>Sharpers,</hi> that ſubſiſt by <hi>Cheating</hi> and <hi>Gaming,</hi> are more deſtructive to the <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> and conſequently occaſion the ruin of more men in it than <hi>Thieves</hi> and <hi>Robbers</hi> can be ſaid to do. Where then lies the difference? But that the Law was made for ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing <hi>Felons,</hi> when there was not ſuch a Vermin known, as now exceed them. 'Tis plain then, That there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains nothing but a Statute to render them the greater Criminals, for otherwiſe they are already ſo in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and then ſending them to <hi>Turkey,</hi> would (I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume) in all reaſon be deem'd an <hi>Act of Grace</hi> to ſave them from <hi>Tyburn;</hi> and that upon a double account. Firſt, In regard that it would afford time for. Repentance to the <hi>one,</hi> and deliverance from Slavery to the <hi>other,</hi> by which means a <hi>Soul</hi> might be ſaved, and a <hi>Body</hi> added to the Kingdom; which, of how contemptible an account ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver this may be reckon'd, to be, yet is it certain, that the loſs of a man is an Injury to the Commonwealth.</p>
            <p>This is no ſelling of <hi>Chriſtians</hi> to the <hi>Turks,</hi> as ſome may at firſt view be apt to believe, but 'tis the redeeming of a Chriſtian by a dead Man; for ſo he ſhould be in the <hi>Eye</hi> of the Law, before he was ſent.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:58535:21"/>
            <p>This way of proceeding, would, doubtleſs, be a great occaſion of Terrour and Diſcouragement to thoſe lewd and profligate ſort of Men, who are become the <hi>Peſt,</hi> and if uncontroul'd, will be the <hi>Bane</hi> of the Nation, and by conſequence, would be a means of preſerving many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds from the <hi>Gallows,</hi> and put all men upon honeſt cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and induſtrious expedients, whereby to compaſs a live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihood. And, to compleat all, to take off the better ſort from their extravagancies, and to neceſſitate the ordinary to apply themſelves to Handicrafts, the moſt conducive method whereby to produce two ſuch deſired effects, would be, to take away the Benefit of the <hi>Clergy,</hi> and in lieu thereof, to enjoin a piece of <hi>Mechanick Work,</hi> of ſome <hi>Trade</hi> or other, to be made by the <hi>Offender.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>THere is now in the Preſs a Diſcourſe entituled, <hi>St.</hi> Paul <hi>the Tentmaker; ſhewing how Religion has in all Ages been promoted by the Induſtrious Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanick.</hi> Written by the ſame Author.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:58535:21"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
